# TIMOTHY MACHULA

# LIFE SCIENCE PROFESSIONAL, DATA SOLUTIONS SPECIALIST

# SUMMARY

Seasoned professional with over 10 years of experience across numerous functions within the drug development lifecycle. I have contributed to novel research in neurodegenerative disease, manufactured cell-based products for bone graft patients, and supported the development of production processes for monoclonal antibodies and viral vector-based gene therapies. While the scenery may have changed, my commitment to excellence has been unwavering through each new challenge.

Throughout my career, I have sought to leverage data and automation to enhance the quality of my work. Now I am seeking a role that will allow me to focus on growing and refining these essential skills while serving the greater life science community. If you are interested in partnering with me in this journey, let's discuss how we can make an impact together.

# CONTACT

PHONE: 352-281-7109

EMAIL:

timothy.machula@gmail.com

## **SKILLS**

#### Data

- Programming: Python, VBA, PHP
- Automation Software: Ignition, Kepware
- Data Storage: MS Access, SQL Server, MySQL, SQLite
- Data Analysis: JMP, MODDE
- Data Visualization: PowerBI, RStudio

#### Life Science

- Analytics: HPLC, BLI, ELISA, PCR, VPE
- Bioreactor Systems: Ambr250, HyPerforma, Xcellerex, Biostat, Univercells

#### **Administrative**

- Finite scheduling
- Resource allocation
- Inventory management
- Material procurement

## **WORK EXPERIENCE**

# Resilience Government Services, Process Development Scientist

2023 - current

- Designed and executed experiments to optimize key process parameters
- Streamlined analytics by automating plate map preparation
- Developed real-time dashboard and notification pipelines for remote monitoring of bioreactor systems

# Thermo Fisher Scientific, Process Development Scientist

2018 - 2022

- Planned and executed batch production runs for AAV and LV platform development
- Developed scheduling and capacity analysis tools to manage department workload
- Created relational database solution to centralize historical data

## RTI Surgical, Cell Technology Specialist Team Lead

2014 - 2017

- Led a team of specialists in a cGMP manufacturing environment
- Implemented tracking system for in-process runs to ensure timely release of material
- Implemented improvements to LN2 storage procedures, increasing sample capacity by >50%

## **EDUCATION**

#### University of Florida – College of Agriculture

B.S., Microbiology and Cell Science